Register of the Rosa Luxemburg and Mathilde Jacob Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Rosa Luxemburg and Mathilde Jacob Papers,
1887-1941
39000
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 1 microfilm reel, 4 envelopes (2.1 linear feet)
Correspondence, annotated daily calendars, and photographs, relating to the German socialist and communist movements, and to the imprisonment of Rosa Luxemburg during World War I. Includes a memoir by Mathilde Jacob, personal secretary to Rosa Luxemburg, entitled "Von Rosa Luxemburg und ihren Freunden" (present in variant typescript forms with annotations, and on microfilm), and correspondence of Mathilde Jacob.
Luxemburg, Rosa, 1871-1919.
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1939.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
Mathilde Jacob, the admirer, friend, confidant, and secretary of Rosa Luxemburg from December 1913 to January 1915, was born in 1873. Between 1913 and 1942 Mathilde Jacob made her living as a public stenographer, typist, and translator. Her years prior to World War I and through the 1920s were devoted to the successive causes of the Social Democratic Party and Communist Party in Germany. She was introduced to these movements by her brother Joseph Jacob, who also helped her obtain such clients as Franz Mehring, Karl Radek, Paul Levy, and Rosa Luxemburg. Mathilde Jacob first met Rosa Luxemburg in December 1913 during her employment as the typist for the publication Sozialdemokratische Korrespondenz. A friendship developed which led to Mathilde's role as Rosa's primary source of external information and material needs during her years of imprisonment from 1914-1918 for opposition to German participation in World War I. Following Rosa Luxemburg's death in 1919, Mathilde Jacob worked for Paul Levy until his death in 1930. In 1942 she was deported to a concentration camp where it is believed that she perished.
Scope and Content
The Rosa Luxemburg-Mathilde Jacob Collection was acquired by the Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace in 1939 by Professor Ralph H. Lutz. These papers, given to Professor Lutz by Mathilde Jacob, comprise some 344 letters, postcards, and telegrams, including 144 letters and postcards from Rosa Luxemburg to Mathilde Jacob, and Mathilde Jacob's manuscript "Von Rosa Luxemburg und ihren Freunden, 1914-1919."
One "Box/folder" of photocopies of lettters from Mathilde Jacob to Jenny Herz was received from the Archiv der sozialen Demokratie in 1989. These letters may not be quoted without written permission of the Archiv der sozialen Demokratie.
Jacob, Mathilde, 1873-1943.; Communism--Germany.; Communism.; Germany--History--Revolution, 1918.; Germany.; Revolutionaries--Germany.; Socialism--Germany.; World War, 1914-1918--Germany.; World War, 1914-1918.
- CORRESPONDENCE FILE, 1897-1922
  Scope and Contents note
  Letters, telegrams, and postcards to Mathilde Jacob from Rosa Luxemburg and others. Also includes a few letters and postcards to Rosa Luxemburg from Mathilde Jacob and Rosa Luxemburg's immediate family. Arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Diefenbach, Hans to Mathilde Jacob
    - Undated. Holograph and typewritten transcript (Box 1: 1)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 June 13. (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 October 16. (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - House, John and Dan McCarton to Rosa Luxemburg, Holograph, 1915 February 28. (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - J.W. to Rosa Luxemburg, Holograph, 1897 August 26. (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Jacob, Mathilde to Rosa Luxemburg
    - Holograph, 1916 July 11. (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - Holograph, 1917 March 18. (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - Holograph, 1917 November 2. (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Jogiches, Leo to Mathilde Jacob, Holograph, 1915 April 15. (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Jaures, Landauer, Bertrand, Vaillant, and others to Rosa Luxemburg, Holograph, 1906 November 4. (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Kautsky, Luise to Mathilde Jacob
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1915 November 1. (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 March 7. (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Liebknecht, Karl to Mathilde Jacob
    - Typewritten transcript, 1915 February. (Box-folder 1: 13)
    - Holograph, and typewritten transcript, 1915 March 25. (Box-folder 1: 14)
    - Holograph, and typewritten transcript, 1915 April 21. (Box-folder 1: 15)
    - Holograph, and typewritten transcript, 1915 September 24. (Box-folder 1: 16)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1915 October 6. (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Holograph, mimeograph, and typewritten transcript, 1915 October 26. (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Liebknecht, Sonja to Mathilde Jacob
    - Undated. Typewritten transcript (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - Undated. Holograph and typewritten transcript (Box-folder 1: 20)
    - Undated. Holograph (Box-folder 1: 21)
    - Undated. Holograph (Box-folder 1: 22)
    - Undated. Holograph and typewritten transcript (Box-folder 1: 23)
    - Holograph, 1916 December 19. (Box-folder 1: 24)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 January 11. (Box-folder 1: 25)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 April 6. (Box-folder 1: 26)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 September 20. (Box-folder 1: 27)
  - Liebknecht, Sonja to Rosa Luxemburg, Holograph, undated (Box-folder 1: 28)
  - Luxemburg, Anna to Mathilde Jacob
    - Typewritten transcript, 1917 May 7. (Box-folder 1: 29)
    - Holograph, 1917 November 11. (Box-folder 1: 30)
  - Luxemburg, Anna to Rosa Luxemburg
    - Undated. Holograph (Box-folder 1: 31)
    - Holograph, 1897 May 4. (Box-folder 1: 32)
    - Holograph, 1897 May 9. (Box-folder 1: 33)
    - Holograph, 1897 July 29. (Box-folder 1: 34)
    - Holograph, 1897 August 4. (Box-folder 1: 35)
    - Holograph, 1897 August 25. (Box-folder 1: 36)
    - Holograph, 1897 August 26. (Box-folder 1: 37)
    - Holograph, 1897 September 2. (Box-folder 1: 38)
    - Holograph, 1897 September 5. (Box-folder 1: 39)
    - Holograph, 1897 September 12. (Box-folder 1: 40)
    - Holograph, 1897 September 24. (Box-folder 1: 41)
    - Holograph, 1897 October 9. (Box-folder 1: 42)
    - Holograph, 1897 November 2. (Box-folder 1: 43)
    - Holograph, 1897 November 2. (Box-folder 1: 44)
    - Holograph, 1901 September 26. (Box-folder 1: 45)
  - Luxemburg, Eduard to Rosa Luxemburg
    - Holograph, 1897 August 4. (Box-folder 1: 46)
    - Holograph, 1897 October 1. (Box-folder 1: 47)
    - Holograph, 1897 October 30. (Box-folder 1: 48)
    - Holograph, 1897 October 31. (Box-folder 1: 49)
    - Holograph, 1899 November 2. (Box-folder 1: 50)
    - Holograph, 1900 January 25. (Box-folder 1: 51)
    - Holograph, 1900 February 22. (Box-folder 1: 52)
    - Holograph, 1900 March 7. (Box-folder 1: 53)
    - Holograph, 1900 April 11. (Box-folder 1: 54)
    - Holograph, 1900 April 20. (Box-folder 1: 55)
  - Luxemburg, Josef to Rosa Luxemburg
    - Holograph, 1897 May 8. (Box-folder 1: 56)
    - Holograph, 1897 August 29. (Box-folder 1: 57)
    - Holograph, 1897 October 30. (Box-folder 1: 58)
    - Holograph, 1897 October 30. (Box-folder 1: 59)
  - Luxemburg, Rosa to Carissmia, Holograph, undated (Box-folder 1: 60)
  - Luxemburg, Rosa to Emilie Jacob
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 January 17. (Box-folder 1: 61)
    - Holograph, 1918 April 27. (Box-folder 1: 62)
  - Luxemburg, Rosa to Mathilde Jacob
    - Undated. Holograph (Box-folder 1: 63)
    - Undated. Holograph (Box-folder 1: 64)
    - Undated. Typewritten transcript (Box-folder 1: 65)
    - Undated. Typewritten transcript (Box-folder 1: 66)
    - Undated. Holograph and typewritten transcript (Box-folder 1: 67)
    - Undated. Holograph and typewritten transcript (Box-folder 1: 68)
    - Undated. Holograph and typewritten transcript (Box-folder 1: 69)
    - Undated. Holograph and typewritten transcript (Box-folder 1: 70)
    - Undated. Holograph and typewritten transcript (Box-folder 1: 71)
    - Undated. Holograph and typewritten transcript (Box-folder 1: 72)
    - Undated. Holograph and typewritten transcript (Box-folder 1: 73)
    - Undated. Holograph (Box-folder 1: 74)
    - (?). Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1913/1914 (Box-folder 1: 75)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1915 March 30. (Box-folder 1: 76)
    - Holograph, 1915 April 9. (Box-folder 1: 77)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1915 April 9. (Box-folder 1: 78)
    - Holograph, 1915 April 14. (Box-folder 1: 79)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1915 April 27. (Box-folder 1: 80)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1915 May 5. (Box-folder 1: 81)
    - (?). Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1915 May 22 (Box-folder 1: 82)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1915 May 29. (Box-folder 1: 83)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1915 June 5. (Box-folder 1: 84)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1915 June 9. (Box-folder 1: 85)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1915 September 24. (Box-folder 1: 86)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1915 October 2. (Box-folder 1: 87)
    - Holograph, 1915 October 5. (Box-folder 1: 88)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1915 October 16. (Box-folder 1: 89)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1915 October 22. (Box-folder 1: 90)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1915 November 6. (Box-folder 1: 91)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1915 November 10. (Box-folder 1: 92)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1915 November 13. (Box-folder 1: 93)
    - Typewritten transcript, 1916 July 11. (Box-folder 1: 94)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1916 October 31. (Box-folder 1: 95)
    - Holograph, 1916 November 5. (Box-folder 1: 96)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1916 November 7. (Box-folder 1: 97)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1916 November 10. (Box-folder 1: 98)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1916 November 13. (Box-folder 1: 99)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1916 December 9. (Box-folder 1: 100)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1916 December 20. (Box-folder 1: 101)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1916 December 22. (Box-folder 1: 102)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1916 December 25. (Box-folder 1: 103)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1916 December 29. (Box-folder 1: 104)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 February 7. (Box-folder 1: 105)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 February 20. (Box-folder 1: 106)
    - Typewritten transcript, 1917 February 22. (Box-folder 1: 107)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 March 17. (Box-folder 1: 108)
    - Typewritten transcript, 1917 March 18. (Box-folder 1: 109)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 March 20. (Box-folder 1: 110)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 March 23. (Box-folder 1: 111)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 March 27. (Box-folder 1: 112)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 March 29. (Box-folder 1: 113)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 April 1. (Box-folder 1: 114)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 April 2. (Box-folder 1: 115)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 April 3. (Box-folder 1: 116)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 April 3. (Box-folder 1: 117)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 April 14. (Box-folder 1: 118)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 April 15. (Box-folder 1: 119)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 April 17. (Box-folder 1: 120)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 April 19. (Box-folder 1: 121)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 April 23. (Box-folder 1: 122)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 April 24. (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 April 25. (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 April 29. (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 May 3. (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 May 9. (Box-folder 2: 5)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 May 10. (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 May 12. (Box-folder 2: 7)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 May 18. (Box-folder 2: 8)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 May 20. (Box-folder 2: 9)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 May 21. (Box-folder 2: 10)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 May 21. (Box-folder 2: 11)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 May 23. (Box-folder 2: 12)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 May 30. (Box-folder 2: 13)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 June 1. (Box-folder 2: 14)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 June 2. (Box-folder 2: 15)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 June 6. (Box-folder 2: 16)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 June 8. (Box-folder 2: 17)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 June 8. (Box-folder 2: 18)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 June 13. (Box-folder 2: 19)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 June 14. (Box-folder 2: 20)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 June 15. (Box-folder 2: 21)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 June 16. (Box-folder 2: 22)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 June 21. (Box-folder 2: 23)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 June 21. (Box-folder 2: 24)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 June 26. (Box-folder 2: 25)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 June 30. (Box-folder 2: 26)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 July 3. (Box-folder 2: 27)
    - Holograph and typewritten trasncript, 1917 July 4. (Box-folder 2: 28)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 July 5. (Box-folder 2: 29)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 July 7. (Box-folder 2: 30)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 July 7. (Box-folder 2: 31)
    - Holograph, 1917 July 10. (Box-folder 2: 32)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 July 26. (Box-folder 2: 33)
    - Typewritten transcript, 1917 July 27. (Box-folder 2: 34)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 July 30. (Box-folder 2: 35)
    - Holograph, 1917 August 6. (Box-folder 2: 36)
    - Typewritten transcript, 1917 August 9. (Box-folder 2: 37)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 August 11. (Box-folder 2: 38)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 August 17. (Box-folder 2: 39)
    - Typewritten transcript, 1917 August 18. (Box-folder 2: 40)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 August 24. (Box-folder 2: 41)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 August 27. (Box-folder 2: 42)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 August 30. (Box-folder 2: 43)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 September 3. (Box-folder 2: 44)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 September 6. (Box-folder 2: 45)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 September 9. (Box-folder 2: 46)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 September 12. (Box-folder 2: 47)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 September 13. (Box-folder 2: 48)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 September 18. (Box-folder 2: 49)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 September 28. (Box-folder 2: 50)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 October 7. (Box-folder 2: 51)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 October 15. (Box-folder 2: 52)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 November 9. (Box-folder 2: 53)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 November 13. (Box-folder 2: 54)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 November 19. (Box-folder 2: 55)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 December 2. (Box-folder 2: 56)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 December 6. (Box-folder 2: 57)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 December 13. (Box-folder 2: 58)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 December 17. (Box-folder 2: 59)
    - Holograph and typerwitten transcript, 1918 January 7. (Box-folder 2: 60)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 January 12. (Box-folder 2: 61)
    - Typewritten transcript, 1918 January 12. (Box-folder 2: 62)
    - Typewritten transcript, 1918 January 14. (Box-folder 2: 63)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 January 17. (Box-folder 2: 64)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 January 20. (Box-folder 2: 65)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 January 26. (Box-folder 2: 66)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 February 1. (Box-folder 2: 67)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 February 7. (Box-folder 2: 68)
    - Typewritten transcript, 1918 February 11. (Box-folder 2: 69)
    - Typewritten transcript, 1918 February 19. (Box-folder 2: 70)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 February 24. (Box-folder 2: 71)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 February 28. (Box-folder 2: 72)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 March 19. (Box-folder 2: 73)
    - Typewritten transcript, 1918 April 6. (Box-folder 2: 74)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 April 13. (Box-folder 2: 75)
    - Typewritten transcript, 1918 April 27. (Box-folder 2: 76)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 April 28. (Box-folder 2: 77)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 May 6. (Box-folder 2: 78)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 May 10. (Box-folder 2: 79)
    - Typewritten transcript, 1918 May 11. (Box-folder 2: 80)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 May 14. (Box-folder 2: 81)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 May 21. (Box-folder 2: 82)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 May 28. (Box-folder 2: 83)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 June 3. (Box-folder 2: 84)
    - Typewritten transcript, 1918 July 11. (Box-folder 2: 85)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 July 19. (Box-folder 2: 86)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 July 22. (Box-folder 2: 87)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 August 9. (Box-folder 2: 88)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 August 14. (Box-folder 2: 89)
    - Typewritten transcript, 1918 August 20. (Box-folder 2: 90)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 September 12. (Box-folder 2: 91)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 September 16. (Box-folder 2: 92)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 September 18. (Box-folder 2: 93)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 October 10. (Box-folder 2: 94)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 November 4. (Box-folder 2: 95)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1918 November 7. (Box-folder 2: 96)
  - Luxemburg, Rosa to Kommandatur der Stadt Berlin, Holograph, undated (Box-folder 2: 97)
  - Luxemburg, Rosa to Herr Rechtsanwalt, Holograph, 1918 November 1. (Box-folder 2: 98)
  - Luxemburg, Rosa and Mathilde Wurm to Mathilde Jacob, Holograph, 1918 January 12. (Box-folder 2: 99)
  - Mehring, Eva to Mathilde Jacob
    - Holograph, 1915 September 27. (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Holograph, 1916 July 28. (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - Holograph, 1916 July 28. (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - Holograph, 1916 July 31. (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Mehring, Franz to Mathilde Jacob
    - Undated. Twelve holographs of notes and letters (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - Holograph, 1914 May 28. (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - Holograph, 1914 June 17. (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - Holograph, 1914 July 22. (Box-folder 3: 8)
    - Holograph, 1914 July 24. (Box-folder 3: 9)
    - Holograph, 1914 July 25. (Box-folder 3: 10)
    - Holograph, 1914 August 21. (Box-folder 3: 11)
    - Holograph, 1914 August 27. (Box-folder 3: 12)
    - Holograph, 1914 September 12. (Box-folder 3: 13)
    - Holograph, 1914 September 16. (Box-folder 3: 14)
    - Holograph, 1914 October 12. (Box-folder 3: 15)
    - Holograph, 1914 October 23. (Box-folder 3: 16)
    - Holograph, 1914 October 24. (Box-folder 3: 17)
    - Holograph, 1914 November 11. (Box-folder 3: 18)
    - Holograph, 1914 November 19. (Box-folder 3: 19)
    - Holograph, 1914 November 23. (Box-folder 3: 20)
    - Holograph, 1915 January 2. (Box-folder 3: 21)
    - Holograph, 1915 January 13. (Box-folder 3: 22)
    - Holograph, 1915 May 4. (Box-folder 3: 23)
    - Holograph, 1915 August 27. (Box-folder 3: 24)
    - Holograph, 1915 August 29. (Box-folder 3: 25)
    - Holograph, 1915 September 15. (Box-folder 3: 26)
    - Holograph, 1915 September 19. (Box-folder 3: 27)
    - Holograph, 1915 October 7. (Box-folder 3: 28)
    - Holograph, 1915 October 16. (Box-folder 3: 29)
    - Holograph, 1915 October 22. (Box-folder 3: 30)
    - Holograph, 1915 November 2. (Box-folder 3: 31)
    - Holograph, 1915 November 5. (Box-folder 3: 32)
    - Holograph, 1916 January 14. (Box-folder 3: 33)
    - Holograph, 1916 April 18. (Box-folder 3: 34)
    - Holograph, 1916 July 4. (Box-folder 3: 35)
    - Holograph, 1916 August 9. (Box-folder 3: 36)
    - Holograph, 1918 March 21. (Box-folder 3: 37)
  - Mehring, Franz to Rosa Luxemburg, Holograph, 1911 December 23. (Box-folder 3: 38)
  - Mullois, Henry to Rosa Luxemburg, Holograph, 1901 September 24. (Box-folder 3: 39)
  - Riachin, Semion to Rosa Luxemburg, Holograph, 1897 July 5. (Box-folder 3: 40)
  - Rosenbaum, Marta to Mathilde Jacob
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 October 26. (Box-folder 3: 41)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 October 28. (Box-folder 3: 42)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 October 31. (Box-folder 3: 43)
  - Rosenbaum, Marta to Rosa Luxemburg, Holograph, 1917 July 17. (Box-folder 3: 44)
  - Schrick, Eva to Mathilde Jacob
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1917 October 28. (Box-folder 3: 45)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1919 January 18. (Box-folder 4: 46)
  - Unknown author to Rosa Luxemburg
    - Undated. Holograph (Box-folder 3: 47)
    - Holograph, 1897 August 27. (Box-folder 3: 48)
  - Wurm, Mathilde to Rosa Luxemburg, Holograph, 1918 November 7. (Box-folder 3: 49)
  - Zetkin, Clara to Leo Jogiches
    - Holograph, 1919 March 9. (Box-folder 3: 50)
    - Typewritten transcript, 1919 March 11. (Box-folder 3: 51)
  - Zetkin, Clara to Mathilde Jacob
    - Undated. Holograph (possibly part of letter dated, 1916 November 20) (Box-folder 3: 52)
    - Undated. Holograph (Box-folder 3: 53)
    - Undated. Holograph (Box-folder 3: 54)
    - Holograph, 1915 March 19. (Box-folder 3: 55)
    - Holograph, 1915 March 23. (Box-folder 3: 56)
    - Typewritten transcript, 1916 February 10. (Box-folder 3: 57)
    - Typewritten transcript, 1916 February 14. (Box-folder 3: 58)
    - Typewritten transcript, 1916 August 14. (Box-folder 3: 59)
    - Typewritten transcript, 1916 August 21. (Box-folder 3: 60)
    - Holograph, 1916 September 1. (Box-folder 3: 61)